{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "During this period, a diplomatic snub toward the ruling government led to the Seikanron debate over a potential invasion of Korea. The Charter Oath laid out the ideals of this period, which proved to be unacceptable to a Satsuma-based group of warriors due to provisions abolishing the practice of feudalism. For ten points, name this period following the Tokugawa Shogunate that featured Western modernizations under a namesake emperor of Japan.",
      "answer": [
        "Meiji Restoration",
        "Meiji Era"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "One of these events was named “Irma’s Injection” and was used to formulate the idea of wish fulfillment. According to one theorist, these events contain manifest and latent content that should be analyzed through therapy. That theorist wrote a book titled The Interpretation of these events, which examined several of these events experienced by the patients of that theorist, Sigmund Freud [FROYD]. For ten points, name these nocturnal events, examples of which include nightmares.",
      "answer": [
        "dreams",
        "equivalents, such as nightmares before it is mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A failed campaign against this man’s troops was bogged down by heavy river quagmires and called the Mud March. This man rose to prominence after the Battle of Seven Pines, where Joseph Johnston was wounded. Shortly after fighting a series of defensive battles at Spotsylvania and the Wilderness, this man spoke at Appomattox Courthouse with Ulysses S. Grant. For ten points, name this commander of the Army of Northern Virginia whose surrender ended the American Civil War.",
      "answer": "Robert E. Lee"
    },
    {
      "question": "A Defense Minister of this country said “it is hard to search for a black cat in a dark room, especially if it’s not there” about the presence of soldiers in a neighboring country. The leader of that neighboring country, Viktor Yanukovych fled to this country after the Euromaidan protests. Soldiers from this country were termed “little green men” and dismissed as being militiamen despite taking Donbass for this country. For ten points, name this country that annexed Crimea in 2014 under Vladimir Putin.",
      "answer": "Russia"
    },
    {
      "question": "In 1939, half of the United States moved this holiday a week earlier, causing a controversy that wasn’t resolved until a 1941 act of Congress. Sarah Josepha Hale helped convince Abraham Lincoln to proclaim this holiday as a federal holiday in 1863. The inspiration for this holiday was an event attended by members of the Wampanoag tribe like Massasoit and Squanto in 1621. For ten points, name this holiday celebrating the first harvest of the Pilgrims in late November.",
      "answer": "Thanksgiving Day"
    },
    {
      "question": "This period roughly began with the establishment of the United Provinces, and it included the creation of Unequal Love and The Proposition by Judith Leyster. Schutterstuks like The Meagre Company by Frans Hals and a painting of the company of Frans Banning Cocq were popular during this period. The Mauritshuis museum in the Hague collects paintings from this period, like those of Vermeer and Rembrandt. For ten points, name this seventeenth-century period of great cultural success in the Netherlands.",
      "answer": [
        "Dutch Golden Age",
        "Gouden Eeuw Dutch"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A weapon that made use of this object was conceptualized by Hermann Oberth and was studied by Nazi engineers at Hillersleben who predicted they could build it within 100 years. A large black stone in reverence to this object was taken to the Palatine Hill by Elagabalus, whose name derives from a cult surrounding this object. During the siege of Syracuse, Archimedes designed a “death ray” that used this body to destroy enemy ships through concentrated heat. Louis the 14th was nicknamed the king of, for ten points, what star?",
      "answer": "the Sun"
    },
    {
      "question": "In a Hopi creation myth, a grandmother figure named Koyangwuti created one of these things to bring the world into existence. In Jewish and Islamic traditions, respectively, one of these things blocked the entrance to a cave, preventing King David or Muhammad from being captured. The original dream catchers were likely inspired by, for ten points, what items that Arachne was condemned to weave in Greek myth?",
      "answer": "spider webs"
    },
    {
      "question": "This group was weakened after repeated attacks by Albert of Mecklenburg’s privateers and the Victual Brothers. As a result of the Treaty of Stralsund, Valdemar IV agreed to give this group control of the fish trade. This group’s cog ships helped carry out trades with outposts like the Steelyard, Visby, and Novgorod. Lubeck became known as the crown jewel of this group’s guilds. For ten points, name this German union that dominated medieval European trade.",
      "answer": "Hanseatic League or Hansa"
    },
    {
      "question": "Preludes to this event included the El Encanto arson and a feint towards Baracoa by the Santa Ana. The president allegedly wanted to “splinter the CIA in a thousand pieces” after their failure in this event. Brigade 2506, a force composed of exiles trained in Guatemala, was tasked with carrying out this event, which prompted its target to ally with the Soviet Union. John F. Kennedy authorized, for ten points, what 1961 failed invasion of Cuba?",
      "answer": "Bay of Pigs invasion"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Ownership of this location, which forms a national park alongside the adjacent Kata Tjuta, was transfered in a 1985 agreement with the Pitjantjatjara [pit-jant-jat-jara] people. In mythology, this location is the site of a battle between the two serpents Kuniya and Liru. Visitors are now banned from climbing this landmark, as it is the site of a Dreamtime track in the Aboriginal belief system. Ayers Rock is an outdated name of, for ten points, what sandstone formation of the Northern Territory in Australia?",
        "answer": "Uluru"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In 1980, one of these Australian canines attacked and killed a two month old baby whose family was vacationing at Uluru. Authorities did not believe the family’s claim, and the child’s mother spent several years in prison before her conviction was overturned.",
        "answer": "dingo"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Robert Livingston and Peter Schuyler [sky-ler] led a convention in this city to oppose Leisler’s Rebellion. Another organization in this city grew out of the Bucktails and lost power after governor William Marcy was defeated in 1838 by William Seward. Thurlow Weed coined the name of that organization led by Martin Van Buren, this city’s “Regency.” The “Join or Die” cartoon was produced at a 1754 meeting in this city that discussed the early goings of the French and Indian War. A 1754 “Congress” met in, for ten points, what capital city of New York?",
        "answer": "Albany"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Another member of Albany’s Schuyler family, Philip, was one of the first senators from New York until he was defeated in a 1791 election by this man, who later killed his son-in-law in a duel in Weehawken, New Jersey.",
        "answer": "Aaron Burr"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A number one hit by this band was censored by the Francisco Franco administration for its lyric “You can get married in Gibraltar, near Spain.” Windows were smashed after advertising for a single by this band was accidentally interpreted as anti-Semitic graffiti in 1968; that single included a song that criticizes people who “go carrying pictures of Chairman Mao.” The songs “Revolution” and “The Ballad of John and Yoko” were released by, for ten points, what band from Liverpool led by John Lennon and Paul McCartney?",
        "answer": "The Beatles"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Paul McCartney claimed he didn’t realize that writing the name of this song on shop windows would stir up memories of Nazism. This song, which was released as a single with “Revolution,” was originally written to reassure John’s son Julian to “Take a sad song and make it better.”",
        "answer": "Hey Jude"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "These people left artifacts behind in the Ukraine’s largest burial mound, the “Black Grave.” These people allegedly executed their enemies with the “blood eagle” method and were employed by the Byzantine Empire as the Varangian Guard. These people sacked Lindisfarne and sailed up the Seine River in longships to attack Paris in 845. The colony of Vinland was founded by, for ten points, what seafaring marauders from Scandinavia?",
        "answer": "Vikings"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The 793 Viking raid on the island of Lindisfarne destroyed one of these facilities, which was founded by Aidan in 634.",
        "answer": [
          "monastery",
          "priory",
          "abbey",
          "church"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "After this field marshal was victorious at a battle near Allenstein, opposing general Alexander Samsonov committed suicide. After Marinus van der Lubbe attempted to burn down a government building, this man was convinced to suspend civil liberties. Erich Ludendorff and this man jointly won the Battle of Tannenberg during World War I. Adolf Hitler was appointed Chancellor by, for ten points, what German politician, war hero, and namesake of a zeppelin that caught fire in 1937?",
        "answer": "Paul von Hindenburg"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Marinus van der Lubbe was blamed for setting fire to this building in Berlin, the meeting place of Germany’s parliament. Hitler had Hindenburg issue the decree banning public opposition to Nazism after the arson of this building.",
        "answer": [
          "Reichstag",
          "Reichstag Fire Decree"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This country is the setting of the novel No One Writes to the Colonel, which depicts an unnamed soldier in the Thousand Days’ War. Riots were sparked after a disgruntled youth assassinated the liberal leader Jorge Eli´ecer Gait´an, leading to La Violencia. The 2016 Nobel Peace Prize was awarded to this country’s president, Juan Manuel Santos, for brokering a treaty that failed after a public referendum. For ten points, name this country where FARC rebels opposed the government in Bogota.",
        "answer": "Colombia"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "No Ones Writes to the Colonel is a novel by this Colombian Nobel laureate who discussed the Medellin cartel in News of a Kidnapping and wrote One Hundred Years of Solitude.",
        "answer": "Gabriel Garcia Marquez"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man, who was sued by Charlotte Dupuy, hired Benjamin Latrobe to design the mansion at his Ashland estate. Domestically, this man’s negotiations resulted in California being admitted as a free state and the prohibition of slavery north of the 36-30 parallel, leading him to be known as the “Great Compromiser.” For ten points, name this Kentucky politician who formulated the Compromise of 1850 and Missouri Compromise.",
        "answer": "Henry Clay"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Henry Clay held this position during the debate over the Missouri Compromise. He left this position to become Secretary of State in the John Quincy Adams administration.",
        "answer": "Speaker of the House of Representatives"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In the short-lived first of these wars, a group of regulars lost a quarter of their men to sharpshooters led by Piet Joubert at Laing’s Nek. Between the two of these wars, Alfred Beit helped orchestrate the Jameson Raid in an attempt to overthrow Paul Kruger. Louis Botha and Jan Smuts participated in the second of these wars as leaders of the Transvaal. The British fought in, for ten points, what wars against the namesake Dutch settlers of South Africa?",
        "answer": [
          "Boer Wars",
          "First and/or Second Boer Wars"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This term was applied to refugee camps established by the British during the Second Boer War, where tens of thousands of Boers died, many of measles and typhoid.",
        "answer": "concentration camps"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Colonial Flordia",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "European power that colonized Florida and ruled it from Madrid.",
          "answer": "Spain"
        },
        {
          "question": "English colony founded by James Oglethorpe that provided a buffer between Florida and the rest of the 13 colonies.",
          "answer": "Georgia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Explorer of Florida who searched for the Fountain of Youth.",
          "answer": "Juan Ponce de Leon"
        },
        {
          "question": "Florida city founded in 1565, the oldest continuously inhabited European city in the US.",
          "answer": "Saint Augustine"
        },
        {
          "question": "Native American tribe that fought a war against Andrew Jackson.",
          "answer": "Seminoles"
        },
        {
          "question": "1819 agreement in which James Monroe’s Secretary of State secured Florida for the United States.",
          "answer": [
            "Adams-Onis Treaty",
            "Transcontinental Treaty"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "City for which the Spanish traded Florida after it was seized in the Seven Years’ War.",
          "answer": "Havana"
        },
        {
          "question": "1832 treaty that forced the aforementioned tribe out of Florida following the Indian Removal Act.",
          "answer": "Treaty of Payne’s Landing"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Muslims in Spain",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Catholic Monarchs, of Castille and Aragon, who persecuted Muslims.",
          "answer": [
            "Ferdinand and Isabella",
            "Ferdinand II of Aragon and Isabella I of Castille"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Strait crossed by Muslim forces who invaded from Morocco.",
          "answer": "Strait of Gibraltar"
        },
        {
          "question": "Tribunal, established in 1478, that persecuted hundreds of thousands of non-Christians in Spain.",
          "answer": "Spanish Inquisition"
        },
        {
          "question": "Caliphate that seized control of Hispania in 711.",
          "answer": "Umayyad Caliphate"
        },
        {
          "question": "800-year-long period that ended in 1492 when Spain defeated the last Muslim kingdom on the Iberian Peninsula.",
          "answer": "Reconquista"
        },
        {
          "question": "Last Muslim kingdom to fall to the Spanish, an emirate on the southern shores of Spain.",
          "answer": "Granada"
        },
        {
          "question": "Former Roman fort that was made into that kingdom’s royal palace by Yusuf I in 1333.",
          "answer": "Alhambra"
        },
        {
          "question": "Last dynastic house to fall to Spain; it was led by Boabdil.",
          "answer": "Nasrid dynasty"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "League of Nations",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "War whose bloodshed inspired a US President to recommend the League.",
          "answer": "World War I"
        },
        {
          "question": "US President who pushed for the League in his Fourteen Points.",
          "answer": "Woodrow Wilson"
        },
        {
          "question": "Swiss city where the League was headquartered and where Conventions against war crimes were signed.",
          "answer": "Geneva"
        },
        {
          "question": "Region re-militarized by Nazi Germany in March 1936, an action essentially ignored by the League.",
          "answer": [
            "Rhineland",
            "descriptions of the land along the Rhine River"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Country led by Haile [“highly”] Selassie, who spoke at the League after Italy invaded this country in 1936.",
          "answer": [
            "Ethiopia",
            "Abyssinia"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Country that retained the Aland Islands in 1921, despite Sweden’s claims.",
          "answer": "Finland"
        },
        {
          "question": "Massachusetts Senator who kept the US out of the League as Chair of the Senate Committee on Foreign Relations.",
          "answer": "Henry Cabot Lodge"
        },
        {
          "question": "Greek island in the Ionian Sea that was bombed by the Italians in 1923, an early example of the League’s weakness.",
          "answer": "Corfu incident"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Three years after his death, this man’s corpse was dug up, hanged alongside Henry Ireton and John Bradshaw, and beheaded, with his head mounted on a stake above Westminster Hall. This man, whose forces (20 pts)",
        "massacred the citizens of Drogheda when they refused to surrender, worked with Thomas Fairfax to win the Battle of (10 pts)",
        "Naseby. This man dissolved the Rump Parliament after leading the New Model Army to victory against Charles I. For ten points, name this Parliamentarian commander who became Lord Protector of England."
      ],
      "answer": "Oliver Cromwell"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In fighting near this city’s San Cosme Gate, future general Ulysses S. Grant disassembled a howitzer and reassembled it in a church, leading to his promotion to captain. The so-called Boy Heroes were killed in this city’s (20 pts)",
        "fortress of Chapultepec by US forces led by Winfield Scott. In the (10 pts)",
        "Marines” Hymn, this city’s battlefields are referred to as the “Halls of Montezuma.” For ten points, name this capital city that was taken by the US in the Mexican-American War."
      ],
      "answer": "Mexico City"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Composer Karlheinz Stockhausen controversially described this event as “the biggest work of art there has ever been.” A “memory space” composed after this event opens with the repeating word (20 pts)",
        "“missing” and includes a tape recording of a list of its victims; that piece is John Adams’ On the Transmigration of Souls. The musical (10 pts)",
        "Come From Away depicts Operation Yellow Ribbon in the Newfoundland town of Gander, where dozens of planes were diverted during, for ten points, what terrorist attack in which nearly 3,000 people were killed in 2001?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "September 11th attacks",
        "9/11",
        "descriptions of any individual attack on 9/11/2001, but"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This battle was preceded by the Battle of Lake Borgne and involved a defensive line behind the Rodriguez Canal. The losing side in this battle stranded many senior officers in no man’s land when they forgot their (20 pts)",
        "ladders. A group of smugglers from Barataria led by Jean Lafitte helped (10 pts)",
        "American forces in this battle defeat and kill Edward Pakenham. For ten points, name this victory for future president Andrew Jackson, a battle that was fought without knowledge of the Treaty of Ghent, which ended the War of 1812."
      ],
      "answer": "Battle of New Orleans"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In 2013, this country finally released the decades-old Sunderlal Committee report, which investigated police actions during the Telangana Rebellion. The 3rd of June Plan established this country’s western border at the (20 pts)",
        "Radcliffe Line. After it achieved independence, this country launched Operation Vijay to reclaim Goa. This country was partitioned from its western neighbor on the request of Muhammad Ali (10 pts)",
        "Jinnah’s Muslim League. For ten points, name this former British colony that gained independence in 1947 after the efforts of Jawaharlal Nehru and Mohandas Gandhi."
      ],
      "answer": "India"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) After Maria Mitchell discovered one of these objects in 1847, Christian VIII of Denmark presented her with a medal. Eight of these objects were discovered by Caroline Herschel, whose brother William discovered the (20 pts)",
        "planet Uranus; one of Caroline’s discoveries was found to be periodic in 1819 by Johann Encke, who now names it. One of these objects appears on the (10 pts)",
        "Bayeux Tapestry and famously appeared in the years of Mark Twain’s birth and death. For ten points, name these astronomical bodies, the most famous of which is named for Edmund Halley."
      ],
      "answer": "comets"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The Salonika Trial may have been a pretext to execute this event’s planner, a man called “Apis.” This event would have failed if its perpetrator had not stopped near the Latin Bridge at Schiller’s (20 pts)",
        "sandwich shop. The July Ultimatum was issued in the aftermath of this event and threatened that Serbia would be attacked within 48 hours. This event was carried out by the (10 pts)",
        "Black Hand and prompted the armies of Germany and Austria-Hungary to mobilize. For ten points, name this 1914 event perpetrated by Gavrilo Princip that is often considered the spark of World War I."
      ],
      "answer": "assassination or murder, shooting, etc. of Archduke Franz Ferdinand do not prompt on partial names"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A politician from this state was gifted a 1947 Cadillac that was paid for with fifty $25 checks; that man served as the longest-serving Speaker of the House and mentored a man who intimidated his colleagues with (20 pts)",
        "“the treatment.” A politician from this state spoke at the University of Michigan, announcing several progressive policies as part of his (10 pts)",
        "“Great Society” in 1964. For ten points, name this home state of Sam Rayburn and Lyndon B. Johnson, the latter of whom was inaugurated as President in this state’s city of Dallas."
      ],
      "answer": "Texas"
    }
  ]
}